Marcos Tirador Curriculum Vitae

CONTACT INFORMATION

Full name: Marcos Manuel Tirador Del Riego Email address: marcosmath44@gmail.com

Website: marcostirador.github.io

SUMMARY

I am a Data Structures and Algorithms instructor in the Computer Science program at the University of Havana, where I also earned my bachelor's degree in Computer Science, under the guidance of Dr. Felix Gotti and Dr. Luis Ramiro Piñeiro. I have an strong inclination for Mathematics. My main research interest is algebra with emphasis on the atomic structure of commutative rings and monoids. During the past 4 years, I have been conducting research in factorization theory under the supervision of Dr. Felix Gotti.

Within computer science, my preference leans towards theoretical computing, though I have also developed strong practical skills. Generally, I relish tackling complex problems that demand creative thinking. These abilities have served me well in the ICPC, where I am a World Finalist.

EDUCATION

Degree	September 2019 — January 2024 Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Top of the class, golden diploma, outstanding in research and academics
University	University of Havana Havana, Cuba
Degree	September 2015 — May 2018 High School Diploma Vocational Pre-University Insitute of Exact Sciences Vladimir I. Lenin Havana, Cuba

WORK EXPERIENCE

Period	January 2024 — Present Day	
Employer	Department of Mathematics and Computer Science	
Job Title	Researcher and instructor	
University	University of Havana	Havana, Cuba
Period	February 2022 — July 2022	
Job Title	Fullstack junior developer	
Employer	D' Clase (private tutoring company)	Havana, Cuba

Marcos Tirador Curriculum Vitae

SCIENTIFIC PUBLICATIONS

(1) On the set of molecules of numerical and puiseux monoids (with Marly Gotti)

In: Rings, Monoids and Module Theory, Springer Proceedings in Mathematics & Statistics book series (Eds. A. Badawi and J. Coykendall). Springer, Singapore. Vol. 382 (2022) 111–125, doi:10.1007/978-981-16-8422-7_5.

(2) Factorization in additive monoids of evaluation polynomial semirings (with K. Ajran, J. Bringas, Bangzheng Li & E. Singer)
Communications in Algebra, Vol. 51:10 (2023) 4347-4362, doi:10.1080/00927872.2023.2208672.

(3) Subatomicity in Rank-2 Lattice Monoids
(with C. Liu & P. Rodriguez)
Journal of Commutative Algebra (to appear). Preprint on ArXiv.

AWARDS

2024	World Finalist at the International Collegiate Programming Contest (ICPC)
2022	Bronze Medal at the XXV Iberoamerican University Mathematical Olympiad
2022	Honorable Mention at the International Mathematics Competition for University Students
2021	Bronze Medal at the International Mathematics Competition for University Students
2021	Gold Medal at the Caribbean Finals of the International Collegiate Programming Contest (ICPC)
2020	Bronze Medal at the Caribbean Finals of the International Collegiate Programming Contest (ICPC)
2018	Bronze Medal at the Iberoamerican Mathematics Olympiad
2017	Honorable Mention at the International Mathematical Olympiad (IMO)
2016	Honorable Mention at the Central American and Caribbean Mathematics Olympiad

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Period	February 2024 — Present Day	
Торіс	Introduction to Programming with Python	
Position	Instructor	
Where	Department of Mathematics and Computer Science	Havana, Cuba

Marcos Tirador Curriculum Vitae

Topic Position	February 2024 — Present Day Data Structures and Algorithms Instructor Department of Mathematics and Computer Science	Havana, Cuba
Topic Position	February 2022 — January 2023 Data Structures and Algorithms Student Assistant Department of Mathematics and Computer Science	Havana, Cuba
Topics Position	May 2019 — August 2019 Number Theory, Algebra and Combinatorics Math Instructor Cuban teams training for international competitions	Havana, Cuba

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages Python, C#, C/C++, JavaScript, Haskell, Prolog, R

(with a higher level of expertise in the first two)

Developer Tools Git, Docker, Linux Systems

Others .NET Core, ASP.NET, Node.js, React, MySQL, Keras

spaCy, NTLK, scikit-learn

SOFT SKILLS

Fast-learning, critical thinking, problem-solving, creativity, teamwork.

Language Skills

Spanish Native Speaker

English Advanced (Certified by Doulingo English Test)